A Guide to the Heslip M. "Happy" Lee Papers, 1915-2003
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Heslip M. "Happy" Lee Papers, 1915-2003
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M322
15.1 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the James Branch Cabell Library in February 2003. Signed deed of gift received in February 2006.
Biographical Information
The Reverend Heslip Malbert "Happy" Lee (1922- ), minister and educator, social and political activist, has spent much of his life working to improve relations between blacks and whites. His life's work is representative of many other like-minded individuals of his generation who were active in the cause for civil rights and equality in the last half of the 20th century. A native of Georgia, Lee's work during the height of the struggle for civil rights brought him to Virginia in the early 1960s where he served as Executive Director of the Virginia Council on Human Relations. In the late 1960s and 1970s he served as a consultant to various educational, urban, and community programs in North Carolina, Georgia, and other localities. [A detailed time line follows this brief biographical sketch.]
Born in rural Polk County, Georgia on February 21, 1922, Heslip Malbert Lee is the son of Mary Camp Lee (1918-1983) and Malbert Warren Lee (1898-1976). Lee had two younger siblings, a sister, Virginia Lee, born 1924, and a brother, Charles Lee, who died at age 2. The Lee family were poor tenant farmers, raising cotton and corn, living without electricity and running water. Lee attended elementary and high school in Polk County. The origin of the name "Happy" began when Lee's sister could not pronounce his first name. She eventually started calling him something that sounded like "Happy." Lee was at Junior College when the name "Happy" began to be used by more than his family. One of his professors considered his name Heslip too hard to remember and asked him if he had a nickname. Lee recounted his sister calling him "Happy." The professor preferred the nickname and it stuck.
In 1941, Lee married Laura McClung (1924- ) of Haralson County. They later had five children: Dwain H. Lee, Glen L. Lee, Joan Lee, Stephen F. Lee (who died in 1994), and Laurie Lee. Happy Lee operated a dairy farm and grocery business in Polk County. Ordained to "preach the Gospel" in October of 1949, Lee served as pastor of the Antioch Baptist Church in July of 1950. He would go on to serve as pastor of nearly a dozen other Baptist churches in Georgia and other states.
Lee received a B.A. Degree in Philosophy in June, 1954 from Mercer University in Macon, Georgia, and a Master of Divinity Degree in 1957 from Colgate-Rochester Divinity School. He became pastor of York Baptist Church, in York, New York, while working in a number of local community organizations. He returned to Georgia and served two years, 1957-1959, as Director of Religious Activities, at Mercer University, in Macon.
Lee served as pastor of First Baptist Church, in Springfield, Virginia, from 1959-1961 and became a member of the Board of Directors of the Virginia Council of Human Relations (VCHR), a biracial state wide organization that worked to foster communication and improved relations between blacks and whites. Lee and his family moved to Richmond when he accepted the post as Executive Director of VCHR. He also served during this time period, 1961-1964, as a member of the Virginia State Advisory Committee to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights.
Lee was extremely active as VCHR's Executive Director. He worked to increase the number of local VCHR groups and overall membership; he spoke to numerous groups in both small and large settings; helped in the desegregation of dozens of public facilities in Virginia; and monitored actions in Prince Edward County, Virginia, where county officials had closed their pubic schools in an effort to block school desegregation.
In late 1964 Lee left Virginia and became Executive Director, Salisbury-Rowan Community Service Council, Inc., in Salisbury, North Carolina and served as Chairman, North Carolina State Advisory Committee to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights. In 1966 he began serving as Vice President for Development, Shaw University, Raleigh and continued to be active in the civil rights field in the state. Beginning in 1968 he would serve for nearly ten years under a variety of titles acting as a consultant to several educational, urban, and community programs in North Carolina, Georgia, and other localities.
Lee retired in 1978 in Cedartown, Georgia, and operated the family jewelry store and farmed. In the 1980s, he served in the "Minister-at-Large" program of the American Baptist Churches with assignments in churches from New York to Utah. In the 1990s he chaired the 7th District (7 Counties) Democratic Party in Georgia and is credited with revitalizing the Polk County Democratic Party.
Timeline: 1922: Born in Polk County, Georgia, February 21, 1922
1939-1941: Employed by Goodyear Textiles, Rockmart, Georgia
1941: Married Laura McClung, July 4, 1941
1941-1950: Operated a dairy farm and grocery business in Polk County, Georgia Served on Polk County Board of Education, chairman of local Community Improvement Project; chairman of local chapter of the Georgia Farm Bureau.
1948-1951: Pastor, Antioch Baptist Church, Cedartown, Georgia
1951-1952: Truett-McConnell Jr. College, Cleveland, Georgia
1952-1954: Mercer University, Macon, Georgia. Received B.A. Degree in Philosophy in June.
1954; Pastor, Belerma Baptist, Hancock County, Georgia (two weeks per month); Pastor Jenkinsburg Baptist, Jenkinsburg, Georgia.
1954-1957: Colgate-Rochester Divinity School, Rochester, New York. Received Master of Divinity Degree, 1957. President of Senior Class, Pastor, York Baptist Church, York, New York. Also worked as a scoutmaster, an officer in the Farm Bureau, a member of the Parent-Teacher Association and volunteered for the local Red Cross drives and a community improvement club.
1957-1959: Director of Religious Activities, Mercer University, Macon, Georgia.
1959-1961: Pastor, First Baptist Church, Springfield, Virginia; Member, Board of Directors, Virginia Council of Human Relations.
1961-1964: Executive Director, Virginia Council on Human Relations, Richmond, Virginia; Member of the Virginia State Advisory Committee to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights.
1964-1966: Executive Director, Salisbury-Rowan Community Service Council, Inc., Salisbury, North Carolina. Served as Chairman, North Carolina State Advisory Committee to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights. Consultant to the U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare in preparing hospitals throughout the Southeast to comply with Medicare regulations.
1966-1968: Vice President for Development, Shaw University, Raleigh, North Carolina; Member, Board of Directors, and Vice President, North Carolina Council on Human Relations; Chairman, North Carolina State Advisory Committee to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights; Consultant to the Office of Economic Opportunity.
1968-1969: Urban Affairs Specialist and Consultant, North Carolina State University, Raleigh, North Carolina. Served as a consultant to various educational, urban, and community programs in North Carolina, Georgia, and other localities.
1969-1971: Deputy Director of Atlanta University, Multi-Purpose Training Center, Atlanta, Georgia which was responsible for the training needs of all local Community Action Agencies in six southern states.
1971-1973: Assistant to the Dean, School of Urban Life, Georgia State University, Atlanta, Georgia. Served as a consultant to various educational, urban, and community programs in North Carolina, Georgia, and other localities.
1973- Program Officer with the Southern Regional Council, Inc., Atlanta Georgia.
1978: Retired, Cedartown, Georgia. Operated a family jewelry store with son Dwain for six years.
1984-1988: Served in the "Minister-at-Large" program of the American Baptist Churches with assignments at: First Baptist Church of Glen Falls, New York (11 months); Madison Avenue Baptist Church, New York, New York (5 months); First Baptist Church, Salt Lake City, Utah; First Baptist Church, Waltham, Massachusetts; Brighton Community Church, Buffalo, New York.
1990s: Farmed for most of the 1990s (a 50 acre+ farm with up to 60 cattle at one point). Chaired the 7th District (7 Counties) Democratic Party. Revitalized the Polk County Democratic Party throughout the 1990s.
2004: In 2004, the Gandhi Foundation of USA, which promotes the philosophies of both Mahatma Gandhi and Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., chose Rev. Lee to be the first non-Indian recipient of the Gandhi Lifetime Achievement Award in recognition of his work in human relations. Rev. Lee received the Gandhi Lifetime Achievement Award on October 9, 2004 at a ceremony held at the historic Ebenezer Baptist Church in the Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. National Historic District.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1915-2003, of Heslip M. "Happy" Lee, consisting principally of correspondence, clippings, photographs, publications, audio and video tapes, and ephemeral items primarily from the late 1950s through the 1980s. The correspondence section of the collection is rich with details on Lee's activities as Executive Director of the Virginia Council on Human Relations in the early 1960s and as a consultant in the late 1960s and 1970s to various educational, urban, and community programs in North Carolina, Georgia, and other localities.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by folder title and chronologically therein. Oversized materials are listed at the end of the container listing.
Contents List
- Advisor's Recognition Certificate, 4-H Club, University System of Georgia, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Album presented to Rev. Happy Lee by Children of First Baptist Sunday School, Glen Falls, New York, 28 April 1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Annual Report, Ford Fellowship Program, 1972-1973, Submitted by Happy Lee. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "An Assessment: The Raleigh, North Carolina Southside Urban Renewal Project," 20 November 1968, A Report of the North Carolina Advisory Committee to the United States Commission on Civil Rights. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Antioch Baptist Church certificate, 3 September 1949, Notes Heslip Lee is licensed to preach. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Antioch Community Improvement Club (Polk County, Georgia), booklet, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Antioch School pupil's report card for Heslip Lee, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Application to the Ford Foundation for Venture Fund Program, 16 February 1971, Submitted by Saint Augustine's College, Raleigh, North Carolina, and written by Happy Lee. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Campus Order: Problem Solving Without Violence," School of Urban Life, Georgia State University, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Chronology of the History of the South to 1895; Chronology of Black American History: 1895-1968, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Church programs - Brighton Community Church, 1988, Includes Chapel Chimes newsletter. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Church programs - First Baptist Church, Glen Falls, New York, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Church programs - First Baptist Church, Salt Lake City, Utah, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Church programs - First Baptist Church, Waltham, Massachusetts, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Church programs - Madison Avenue Baptist Church, New York, New York, 1985, Includes petition regarding problem of prostitution. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Church programs - miscellaneous, 1960, 1965, 1967, 1980, 1982, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Church programs - Unitarian Church Programs, 1964, 1968, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Clergyman's Record, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Colgate Divinity School (Rochester, New York), miscellaneous items, 1955-1957, Includes bulletin, 1957, commencement exercises program, 1957, and grade card of Happy Lee, 1955-1956. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1955-1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  This spiral bound notebook of correspondence contains over 200 letters that were arranged in chronological order by Lee. Most are addressed to Lee but there are about a dozen letters by Lee to others. Much of the correspondence concerns Lee's work as director of the Virginia Council on Human Relations (VCHR) 1960-1964; as Executive Director of the Salisbury-Rowan Community Service program in Salisbury, North Carolina, 1964-1966; and as Vice-President for Development at Shaw University, Raleigh, North Carolina, 1966-1967. Letters worth nothing include: David H. Scull, May 27, 1959, inviting Lee to serve as Executive Director of the Virginia Council on Human Relations; Richard Hocking, Chairman, Georgia Council on Human Relations, December 14, 1960, asking Lee to become its Executive Director; Leo E. Cloutier, Executive Vice-President, General Manager, Richmond Virginians baseball team, August 12, 1963, concerns the desegregation of Parker Field, Richmond, Virginia; Heslip M. Lee, September 26, 1963, addressed to Lee White, Special Assistant to the President of the United Sates, detailing the work of the VCHR, the desegregation of theaters and restaurants in Virginia, the situation in Prince Edward County, and Lee's invitation for the president to visit Richmond to deliver an address [an invitation to President Johnson to deliver an address from Lee and others is dated January 20, 1964]; Wyatt Tee Walker, Executive Assistant, Southern Christian Leadership Conference, October 22, 1963, thanking Lee for the "greatest convention in SCLC's History" and noting "the full use of the John Marshall's [a Richmond hotel] facilities represents a significant break-through in human relations;" and Norman Lee Williams, December 12, 1963, addressed to Rev. John J. Mahon, President, Richmond Council, Richmond-Petersburg Area Council on Human Relations, concerning William's preference for "the segregated way of life." The notebook also contains reports by Lee as a consultant to CAP (Community Action Program), the federal anti-poverty program, on his visits to localities throughout the South. Correspondents also include individuals who were active in desegregation efforts in Virginia, especially Prince Edward County: members of the American Friends Service Committee, Inc., Cambridge Massachusetts; J. Rupert Picott, Executive Director, Virginia Teachers Association; Willie Carter, Prince Edward County Branch NAACP; J. Kenneth Morland, Chairman, Department of Sociology and Anthropology, Randolph-Macon Women's College, Lynchburg, Virginia; and L. Francis Griffin, Minister, First Baptist Church, Farmville, Virginia.
- Correspondence, 1958-1961, 1965, 1971, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  This folder has nearly thirty letters of correspondence with individuals including those associated with the Colgate Rochester Divinity School, Rochester, New York; Mercer University, Macon, Georgia; and the Southern Regional Council, Inc., Atlanta, Georgia, addressing their offer of having Lee serve as head of the Georgia Council. The folder also contains letters from Lee to others, including Mr. and Mrs. Sydney Lewis of Richmond, Virginia. The letters were arranged in chronological order by Lee.
- Correspondence 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  This folder contains ten letters addressed to Lee and fourteen written by him during his tenure as pastor of the First Baptist Church, Springfield, Virginia, 1959-1961. The letters were placed in chronological order by Lee. Many of the letters focus on his resignation as pastor to become Executive Director of the Virginia Council of Human Relations in Richmond. In a mimeographed copy of one letter from 1960, addressed to a college freshman woman and a member of his church, Lee discussed his views about Lent, Ash Wednesday, and Good Friday. This letter was to be used for discussion with a group of college students belonging to various different denominations.
- Correspondence, 1961, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  This spiral bound notebook of correspondence arranged chronological by Lee contains sixty-two letters, one from 1961, the others date from December of 1962 through December of 1963. It was during this time period, 1961-1964, that Lee served as Executive Director of the Virginia Council on Human Relations (VCHR). A significant number of letters are carbon copies sent by Lee to various recipients. Several of the letters are from or addressed by Lee to individuals at Mercer University, Macon, Georgia. Lee graduated from the school in 1954. He also worked for two years as Director of Religious Activities working with students and reporting to the president of the school. Some of these letters concern what Lee described in a May 3, 1963 letter to the president of the school as "the removal of racial bars for admission to Mercer." The notebook contains a report by Mercer University President Rufus Harris dated April 18, 1963 to the trustees of the school on the need to racially integrate the University (a letter dated October 9, 1963 notes that Mercer University "just admitted three negroes"). Letters dated June 13, 1963 and July 23, 1963 concern Carl Braden (1914-1975), a noted white civil rights and political activist whose work in Virginia may have been considered counter productive by the VCHR. There is also correspondence in September and October of 1963 discussing a possible "march on Nashville" (home to the Southern Baptist Convention) to highlight differences between progressive and conservative Baptists.
- Correspondence and reports, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  These items were originally bound together and include a significant number of materials documenting the work of Lee, the Virginia Council on Human Relations (VCHR), and the state of race relations in Virginia for these two years. The items were arranged in chronological order by Lee. This folder contains numerous reports by Lee on the work of the VCHR including monthly reports that highlight his daily activities. Other notable materials noting include a report by Lee on Prince Edward County, Virginia, dated January 9, 1962; text of "From Lent to Easter" by Lee, sermon published in the Richmond News Leader, April 4, 1962, as part of their weekly "sermonette" series; baccalaureate sermon delivered by Lee at Saint Paul's College, Lawrenceville, Virginia, May 27, 1962; text of "Speech for Annual Meeting" by Lee, November 23-24, 1962; letter by Lee to Lee C. White, Assistant Special Counsel to the President, inviting the president to Richmond; text of keynote address delivered by Lee entitled "Projecting a New Image in Practical Arts and Vocational Education" at the Eighth Annual Conference of Vocational and Practical Arts Teachers, June 24-27, 1963, at the Virginia State College, Petersburg, Virginia; and the text of Lee's sermon "Moving Forward Through Community Service" given at the Zion Hill Baptist Church, Petersburg, Virginia, fall of 1963. Also of interest is correspondence relating to the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) meeting that was held in Richmond at the John Marshall Hotel in September of 1963. The owners of the hotel were concerned about "adverse publicity" that the SCLC convention might attract.
- Correspondence, reports, and publications, 1964 and n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  These materials were originally bound together and include reports by Lee and correspondence (20 letters, 2 telegrams) documenting the work of Lee and the Virginia Council on Human Relations (VCHR) during the year 1964. One letter addressed to Lee by Edward E. Haddock, a Richmond doctor, dated August 14, 1964, discussed Haddock's attendance at a meeting of the National Citizens Committee in Washington D.C. that focused on the implementation of the recently passed Civil Rights Acts. Haddock informed Lee "I was quite proud to have an opportunity to speak in our work-shop session where I told the group that the best that had ever happened in Richmond to help us with our problems was when you came on the scene. I went into some detail about how you have worked to enable miracles to come forth quietly." Other materials include notes by Lee for his remarks at the Prince Edward County NAACP Freedom-Labor Day event, September 7, 1964 and notes for a speech he gave at St. Stephen's Episcopal Church, February 17, 1964, entitled "Sociological Implications of the Present Situation." The folder also contains a photocopy of the program for the VCHR sponsored event entitled "Consultation of Virginia Lawyers" held in Richmond, January 11, 1964, that included speakers Robert R. Merhige, Jr. (who later served as a Federal judge on the U. S. District Court, Eastern District of Virginia, from 1967 through 1998) and Nicholas Katzenbach (who was then U.S. Deputy Attorney General and directed federal enforcement of desegregation, later served as Attorney General 1965-1967 and then as Under Secretary of State 1966-1969).
- Correspondence, reports and other materials, July 1965-December 1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Nearly 60 letters and other materials are contained in this folder that was once bound. These items document Lee's work during the years 1965 and 1966 as he served as Executive Director of the Salisbury-Rowan Community Service program in Salisbury, North Carolina. The program was part of the War on Poverty initiative by the Federal government. At this time, Lee also served as a consultant on various projects in the South connected to the War on Poverty (including the Office of Equal Health Opportunities) and as Acting Chairman of the North Carolina State Advisory Committee to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights. Items of note include a three page report on a meeting held May 30, 1966 at a bakery in Salisbury whose owner was critical of the Salisbury-Rowan program.
- Correspondence, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Approximately 85 letters in this folder date from 1967 and were once bound. They contain a significant amount of correspondence and other materials related to Lee's work as the Acting Chairman of the North Carolina State Advisory Committee to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights and his work as Vice-President for Development for Shaw University, Raleigh, North Carolina. The items were arranged in chronological order by Lee. Also included are reports by Lee as a consultant to CAP (Community Action Program), the federal anti-poverty program, on his visits to localities throughout the South. Other items worth noting include a letter from Joseph L. Berry dated May 13, 1967 regarding the North Carolina Council on Human Relations and their involvement in a labor dispute in the textile industry in North Carolina. Berry writes "Let us not reduce our effectiveness by making the same mistake Dr. King has made." A June 27, 1967 letter by Lee includes details on his actions over the past year to raise funds for Shaw University as well as his proposal for another full time person in development.
- Correspondence, October 1967-May 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)